<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Thoughts, opinions, and research projects (Posts about carbon sequestration)</title><link>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/categories/carbon-sequestration.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 14:59:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Will reservoirs be clogged by salt precipitation during CO2 dryout</title><link>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/posts/zhang2016clogging.html</link><dc:creator>Shuo Zhang</dc:creator><description>&lt;!--
 .. title: Will reservoirs be clogged by salt precipitation during CO2 dryout
 .. slug: zhang2016clogging
 .. date: 2017-03-25 
 .. tags: carbon sequestration, reservoir clogging, dry out
 .. link: 
 .. description: 
 .. type: text
 --&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sequestration, well injectivity is a critical issue. The injected dry gas, at low water-vapor partial pressure, will equilibrate with the formation brine and water will evaporate into the flowing CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; stream. Water salinity increases as a result and eventually precipitates out salt. This effect has been reported for gas producing wells in reservoirs of high salinity brine &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Kleinitz, Dietzsch, and Köhler 2003)&lt;/span&gt; and during storage of natural gas &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="place1984unusual"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. The source of extra pressure build-up in the Ketzin &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Baumann, Henninges, and De Lucia 2014)&lt;/span&gt; and Snohvit &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Grude, Landrø, and Dvorkin 2014)&lt;/span&gt; CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; storage projects is partly assigned to salt precipitation. Probably because few large-scale pilots have been built for CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sequestration, direct observations of salt precipitation have not been available at field scale. Right now we rely on numerical simulations &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Giorgis, Carpita, and Battistelli 2007; K. Pruess and Müller 2009; Qiao et al. 2014; Zeidouni, Pooladi-Darvish, and Keith 2009)&lt;/span&gt; and experimental studies &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Pearce et al. 1996; Andre, Peysson, and Azaroual 2014; Ott, Roels, and De Kloe 2015; S. M. Roels et al. 2016; Muller et al. 2009; Tang et al. 2015; Y. Wang et al. 2010)&lt;/span&gt; to determine the key parameters involved so that we can correctly model well injectivity on the field scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/Andre2014Field.jpg" alt="@andre2014well" style="width: 500px;"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field-scale simulations require input on flow physics such as the porosity-permeability relationship. Porosity change can be calculated simply from the volume of precipitated salt. The change of permeability, however, is a complex problem. The most widely used porosity-permeability relationship in current numerical simulations is the tube-in-series model proposed by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt;. This model allows to reach zero permeability even if porosity is not nil. In this model, pore geometry is conceptualized as a series of one-dimensional tubes that are identical to each other. Each tube consists of wide and narrow segments, and the permeability value is dominated by the local radii of the narrowest part of the tube. When salt precipitates on the tube walls, the local permeability for the narrow segments decreases much more rapidly than those for the wide segments. The result is clogging of the entire tube. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt; used this relationship in their numerical simulator TOUGH2 &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(K. Pruess 1991)&lt;/span&gt; to explore the role of different parameters in the salt precipitation process and found that injectivity could be reduced significantly. For the given parameter values used in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt;, reservoir permeability is reduced to zero when precipitated salt occupies 10% of the pore space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/Tubes.png" alt="Verma and Pruess (1988)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recent publications related to salt precipitation in CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; storage have used the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; porosity-permeability relationship, but with different parameter values from fitting of experimental data &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Andre, Peysson, and Azaroual 2014; Muller et al. 2009; Bacci, Durucan, and Korre 2013; Giorgis, Carpita, and Battistelli 2007; Guyant et al. 2015; Ott, Roels, and De Kloe 2015)&lt;/span&gt;. Exceptions are the papers by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Zeidouni, Pooladi-Darvish, and Keith (2009)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Tang et al. (2015)&lt;/span&gt; where they use the simple Kozeny-Carman grain model &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(P. C. Carman 1956; P. Carman 1997)&lt;/span&gt; based on spheres to calculate changes in permeability due to changes in porosity. Recently, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; points out that the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation between permeability change and salt precipitation is based on a single phase flow model, but CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sequestration involves two phases. They conceptualize the porous media as a series of tubes with different sizes, and develop a new relation between permeability change and salt precipitation that considers the fact that salt precipitation occurs only in the pore space occupied by brine during the precipitation process. This model is in agreement with observations by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt; in which they conduct core flooding experiments and claim that there is no transport mechanism of liquid water vapor across the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; brine interface and hence no transport mechanism of salt into the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; flow channels. These CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; flow channels will stay open since salt precipitates in the residual brine phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; model in which permeability change is a single function of porosity change, the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model relates permeability change to not only porosity change, but also pore size distribution and water saturation at which precipitation takes place. The &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model is also a continuum-scale relation in that all parameters involved are available in current reservoir simulators. It is thus possible to implement this relation in a reservoir simulation code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/Ott2015Concept.jpg" alt="Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-porosity-permeability-relationships-are-used-in-recent-studies"&gt;What porosity-permeability relationships are used in recent studies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Bacci, Korre, and Durucan (2011)&lt;/span&gt; conducted core flooding experiments with supercritical CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and used the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; model to fit the experimental data. The reduced porosities from several experiments were plotted against permeability reductions. However, readers need to note that in this plot each data point is an averaged porosity and permeability of the entire core. In most such experiments, salt precipitation is heterogeneous inside the core and more salt precipitates close to the injection zone. In numerical simulations of core flooding experiments, the core is discretized into a number of grid blocks. Porosity change is monitored in each grid block. The porosity-permeability relationship is also applied in each grid block to calculate the corresponding permeability change. Thus, the porosity-permeability relationship obtained from the average porosity and permeability measurements of the entire core does not necessarily represent the true porosity-permeability relationship for each grid cell, especially when salt precipitation has large variations through the core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt; used the same &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; model to fit their experimental data, but introduced a new term which was the lowest value to which permeability can be reduced by precipitation. They also argued that the maximum pore volume that could be filled by precipitate was the volume corresponding to the residual brine saturation, thus the critical porosity was 0.8 (assuming residual water saturation was 0.2). Using these constraints, they determined a rather large exponential term equal to 10.1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Giorgis, Carpita, and Battistelli (2007)&lt;/span&gt; used the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; as a regression function to fit their extended Verma and Pruess model, and determined an exponential term equal to 4.1 and a critical porosity of 0.3. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt; chose parameters similar to what was used in another study of permeability changes due to precipitation of amorphous silica at a geothermal injection well in the Philippines &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(T. Xu et al. 2004)&lt;/span&gt;, with the exponential term being equal to 2 and the critical porosity equal to 0.9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Tang et al. (2015)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Zeidouni, Pooladi-Darvish, and Keith (2009)&lt;/span&gt; used the simple Kozeny-Carman grain model based on spheres to calculated changes in permeability due to changes in porosity. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Zeidouni, Pooladi-Darvish, and Keith (2009)&lt;/span&gt; used the equation with no tunable parameters, while &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Tang et al. (2015)&lt;/span&gt; included an exponential coefficient and used experimental data to determine its value. Exponent 2.4 was demonstrated through the data regression with the minimum deviation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="mohamed2013fluid"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; used both the Carman-Kozeny relation and power law to fit experimental data. They found that the exponent terms cover a large range of values, from around 4 to as high as 400. The significant reduction of permeability corresponding to the large exponents are mainly because of the pore-throat plugging by fines migration due to the presence of silicate minerals in dolomite rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to us that, compared to other models, the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model provides a more physics sound relation for porosity and permeability evolution, since it honors the physical process of salt precipitation in a two-phase system and is based on well-established relative permeability relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="29%"&gt;
&lt;col width="50%"&gt;
&lt;col width="20%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Publication&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Porosity-permeability relation&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align="right"&gt;Relation type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi/\phi_0-\phi_r}{1-\phi_r})^2,\phi_r=0.9$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Verma and Pruess&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Andre, Peysson, and Azaroual (2014)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi/\phi_0-\phi_r}{1-\phi_r})^2,\phi_r=0.91$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Verma and Pruess&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0} =(\dfrac{\phi/\phi_0-\phi_r}{1-\phi_r})^\tau (1-k_c/k_0) +k_c/k_0$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Verma and Pruess&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Giorgis, Carpita, and Battistelli (2007)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi/\phi_0-\phi_r}{1-\phi_r})^\tau,\phi_r=0.3,\tau=4.1$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Verma and Pruess&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Zeidouni, Pooladi-Darvish, and Keith (2009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi}{\phi_0})^3 (\dfrac{1-\phi_0}{1-\phi})^2,\phi_0=0.12$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Carman-Kozeny&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Y. Wang et al. (2010)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi}{\phi_0})^c (\dfrac{1-\phi_0}{1-\phi})^2,c=2.4$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Carman-Kozeny&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="mohamed2013fluid"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi}{\phi_0})^c (\dfrac{1-\phi_0}{1-\phi})^2,c=4.53\sim445.0$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Carman-Kozeny&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="mohamed2013fluid"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=(\dfrac{\phi}{\phi_0})^n,n=5.17\sim448.2$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="right"&gt;Power Law&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id="liu2013permeability-model"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt;, the pore space of a porous medium is conceptualized as cylindrical capillaries with a continuous distribution of radii &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. A given capillary can be either water-filled or completely dry, depending on the saturation state of the medium. With this geometric idealization, the capillary pressure-water saturation curve can be interpreted to represent continuous cumulative pore-size distribution (PSD). In a given portion of the porous medium (in computational terms this would be a cell within the modeled domain), at any time the water content is known. Due to precipitation/dissolution, the pore volume will change and thus the capillary pressure curve changes also. The maximum radius up to which pores are water-filled and therefore affected by mineral reactions can be calculated from capillary pressure head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$r = \frac{1}{h},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt; is the threshold radius and &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; is the capillary pressure head. The corresponding effective water saturation &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$S=\frac{\theta-\theta_{r}}{\theta_{s}-\theta_{r}},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the wetting-phase content (the ratio of wetting-phase volume to the corresponding bulk volume of a porous medium), and subscripts &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt; refer to saturated and residual values for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capillary pressure head &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; is given as a function of effective wetting-phase saturation by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="van1980closed"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; = [1 + (&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;m=1-1/n&lt;/em&gt; are empirical parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before mineral reactions, the relative permeability of the wetting phase &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; can be expressed by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Mualem (1976)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_r=S^{1/2} [\dfrac{\int_0^s (1/h(x))dx}{\int_0^1 (1/h(x))dx}]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/2&lt;/sup&gt;[1 − (1 − &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes in pore geometry during salt precipitation is a complex process. Here a strict dependency of salt precipitation on solution concentrations is assumed, in other words, the amount of precipitated salt in a given pore is linearly dependent on its pore volume. Also the change in pore volume is assumed to be uniform within a given pore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denoting the brine content and corresponding effective saturation at the time when mineral reaction starts as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the ratio of pore volume after chemical reactions to that before reactions, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, can be defined as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\beta=\dfrac{\theta_p-\theta_{salt}}{\theta_p},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the content of precipitated salt, defined as the volume of salt precipitation divided by the bulk volume of a porous medium. The ratio &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of the hydraulic radius (for a pore after precipitation) to its original radius can be approximated to be a power function of the corresponding volume ratio &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Liu et al. 2013)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is an empirical parameter equal to 4.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In previous studies &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Verma and Pruess 1988)&lt;/span&gt;, changes in pore volume were modeled as affecting the entire pore spectrum despite the fact that salt precipitation occurs only in the water-filled pores. Here, instead, only changes in pore volumes in the wet part of the porous medium are translated to pore radii.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a given portion of the porous medium, at any time the water saturation is known. The maximum radius up to which pores are water-filled and therefore affected by salt precipitation is calculated as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;[&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; − 1]&lt;sup&gt;−1/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The radius &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; divides the pore spectrum into a dry, inert part and a wet reactive part, which has to compensate for the change in pore volume. For the calculation of the new PSD, only the pore radii of the wet pore space are multiplied by the proportionality factor &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cumulative PSD represents the relative volume of drainable pores with a radius equal to or smaller than &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. The drainable pore-size density function is obtained by differentiation of the cumulative PSD with respect to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$f(r)=\dfrac{d\theta(r)}{dr}.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We denote the new PSD function after salt precipitation as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, the new water content as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the new radius as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Recall that we define the volume ratio before and after reactions as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the radius ratio as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Thus, we have &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$f^*(r^*)=\dfrac{d\theta^*(r^*)}{dr^*}=\dfrac{\beta}{\delta}f(\dfrac{r^*}{\delta}).$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt;, we have &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^{r_p^*}r^*f^*(r^*)dr^*+\int_{r_p}^\infty rf(r)df}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the threshold radius below which pores are occupied by water, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which is the threshold radius post mineral reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^{r_p} \delta\beta rf(r)dr+\int_{r_p}^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the mathematical relation &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="van1980closed"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$f(S)=\dfrac{\int_0^r rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}=1-(1-S^{1/m})^m,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[(\delta\beta-1)(1-(1-S^{1/m})^m)+1]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/PoreBundleModel.png"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="compare-with-experimental-measurements"&gt;Compare with experimental measurements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Porosity-permeability relations fitted from experimental data provide empirical equations for field scale simulations, and sometimes such empirical relations are the most reliable options. However, due to the heterogeneity of salt precipitation in core flooding experiments, using the average porosity and permeability reduction measured for the entire core may not be a valid approach. Several experimental studies &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Peysson, Andre, and Azaroual 2014; Ott, Roels, and De Kloe 2015)&lt;/span&gt; have observed that the decrease in water saturation at the injection surface induces brine capillary back flow that transfers the brine toward the injection surface. Salt accumulates near the injection surface and precipitates when saturation is reached. In numerical simulations of such experiments, the representative element volume (REV) is defined as one thin slice of the core. In &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Andre, Peysson, and Azaroual (2014)&lt;/span&gt;, the 60 mm long core was represented by 60 grid cells, with each cell being 1.0 mm thick, and most salt precipitation accumulated in the first few millimeters of the core, close to the injection zone. The porosity-permeability relationship is an equation that describes the physics in each REV, which is the 1.0 mm slice in this case. Using the porosity and permeability data for the entire core to fit a porosity-permeability relationship is not conceptually consistent with the REVs in numerical models. In fact, the capillary back flow and precipitation of salt near the injection zone can be reproduced by continuum-scale numerical models with two-phase Darcy flow, capillary pressure, and thermodynamics of salt precipitation. The porosity-permeability relationship should not double account for the rapid permeability reduction by heterogeneous precipitation. Given the difficulty in measuring porosity and permeability change in each slice of a core sample, the best data for fitting the porosity-permeability relation comes from experiments where salt precipitation is homogeneous along the core. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt; found that there is a critical flow rate above which salt precipitates homogeneously. At high injection rate, the viscose force increases, and the capillary force becomes less important to drive back flow. Using a flow rate of 4.4 ml/min, they observed a uniform salt saturation of 0.04 throughout the core after drying. However, such experimental data is rare, and in most experiments heterogeneous precipitation of salt is observed &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Peysson, Andre, and Azaroual 2014; Andre, Peysson, and Azaroual 2014; Ott, Roels, and De Kloe 2015)&lt;/span&gt;. One other option is to deliberately cut off the zone close to injection inlet and examine the rest of the core where precipitation is relatively uniform. In order to measure the permeability of a fraction of the core, pressure needs to be measured not only at the inlet and outlet, but also along the core length at discrete locations. Such measurements can be achieved by using side taps as in the setup in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Y. Wang et al. (2010)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/Ott2015Ss.jpg" alt="Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; used the experimental work by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Y. Wang et al. (2010)&lt;/span&gt; to compare their predictions on permeability change with experimental observations. The flood experiments were performed on brine saturated cores that were 1.5 inch in diameter and 1 foot longe. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; selected the data for the core segment between two side taps (3cm-13.05cm) and avoided the zone near the injection inlet (0-3cm). The ratio of the new permeability for this segment after CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; dry-out to the initial permeability measured in the experiment is 0.55, and the value predicted from the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model is between 0.50 and 0.57. The prediction from the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model is indeed close to the experimental measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we also calculate the predicted permeability ratio using the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; model and compare it with the experimental measurement in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Y. Wang et al. (2010)&lt;/span&gt;. In the laboratory test the salt mass fraction in brine &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; was 25.0%. The core was initially saturated with brine, and the breakthrough of supercritical CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; happened at about 0.3 pore volume (PV) of injection. Since the displaced brine had little time to interact with CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, it is reasonable to assume that there was no salt precipitation form the displaced brine, and the remaining brine in the core when precipitation starts was 0.7 PV. The brine production slowed down greatly after the breakthrough, and CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; continued to flood through the core for all the remaining brine to evaporate into. In total, about 176 PV of supercritical CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; was injected into the core. Thus, the amount of salt precipitation at the end of flooding is estimated to be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{\rho_{aq}}{\rho_s} X_{salt} \times 0.7 PV = 0.0959 PV?$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ρ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 1180&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the aqueous phase density and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ρ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 2153&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the density of precipitated salt. Using the above equation where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 − 0.0959 = 0.9041, &lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.9&lt;/span&gt;, we have &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\dfrac{k}{k_0}=0.001681$&lt;/span&gt;. Obviously this overestimates the reduction of permeability compared to results using the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model (0.50-0.57) and measured in the experiment (0.55).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/WangCore.JPG" alt="Y. Wang et al. (2010)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Y. Wang et al. (2010)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="does-salt-precipitate-in-the-aqueous-phase"&gt;Does salt precipitate in the aqueous phase?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key assumption in the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation is that salt precipitates in the water occupied pore space. The assumption is reasonable given that salt initially dissolves in water and can only precipitates out of water. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt; conducted core flooding experiments of CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; replacing brine in a sandstone sample and used micron CT to image the distribution of solid salt and the initial CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in the pore space. Their 3D representation of the solid salt distribution and the early CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; percolation pattern showed that both patterns occupied complementary space and overlapped by less than 5% of the common cross section. This indicated that salt precipitated in the vicinity of the initially CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; occupied volume, leaving the initial CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pathways essentially open. They thus claim that there is no transport mechanism of liquid water vapor across the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-brine interface and hence no transport mechanism of salt into the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; channels, and the flow channels stay open since salt precipitates in the residual brine phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Miri et al. (2015)&lt;/span&gt; conducted lab-on-chip experiments to explore the dynamics of salt precipitation at the pore-scale, and reached opposite conclusions. They found that salt aggregates attracted water from the adjacent network grains via continuous water films around the mineral grains through surface energy effects, and this enabled continued feeding of the evaporating front with fresh brine, thus allowing the continued growth of salt on these aggregates. The result of this mechanism was a large accumulation of salt in the form of aggregates in the gas phase. An important requirement for this self-enhancing mechanism was the interconnected films that were relative thick on the surface of grains. However, the existence of such thick water film and their practical significance in hydraulic conductivity needs further investigation. The flow mechanism associated with this significant film flow is not considered in this study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/Ott2015.jpg" alt="Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="numerical-simulation"&gt;Numerical Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By reviewing how the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relations are derived, it is clear that the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation is based on the capillary tube concept and assumes that mineral precipitation happens in all tubes, and that all tubes are identical. The &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation takes into account the pore size distribution function (m), and distinguishes between the water occupied tubes and gas occupied tubes (using water saturation). In CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sequestration, the simulations obviously involve two phases, i.e., CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; gas and water. For example, if water saturation is 50% when water evaporates into the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; plume, the precipitated salt should clog the water occupied tubes, which are theoretically the small ones since water is the wetting phase. So only this 50% pore volume should be affected by salt precipitation. The &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation distributes the precipitated salt uniformly in all tubes. They assume that all tubes are identical but part of each tube has a small radius, so the distributed salt clogs the narrow part of the tubes first, thus clogging the entire porous medium. This approach predicts dramatic reduction of permeability by salt precipitation in their numerical simulation. However, different results are possible if the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation is used. In this paper we implement the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation in the TOUGH2 reservoir simulator, and re-run the reservoir simulation similar to the one in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt;. Results using both the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt; model and the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model are presented in this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/WorkFlow.png"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="model-setup"&gt;Model setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numerical simulations described here are performed using the general purpose reservoir simulation code TOUGH2, coupled with the fluid property module ECO2N &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(K. Pruess and Spycher 2007)&lt;/span&gt;. Two simulations are conducted, one using the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation for porosity and permeability and the other using the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation. All other input parameters are identical for the two simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consider a basic problem of CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; injection into a saline aquifer under conditions that may be encountered in brine aquifers at a depth of the order of 1.2 km. A CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; injection well fully penetrates a homogeneous, isotropic, infinite-acting aquifer of 100 m thickness, at conditions of 12 MPa pressure, 45 C temperature, and a salinity of 0.25 by weight. Porosity is set at 24.02%, and permeability at 1.66 Darcy. The residual water saturation is assumed to be 0.30. The relative permeability and capillary pressure have been calculated using the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(&lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="van1980closed"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; models. The relative equations and parameters are listed in Table 1. CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is injected at a constant rate of 100 kg/s. This problem is similar to the model in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The well is modeled as a circular grid element of R = 0.3 m. The numerical grid is extended to a large distance of 100 km, so that the system would be infinite-acting for the time period simulated (10,000 days, 27.38 years). The upper and lower boundaries of the formation are closed, simulating impermeable layers at the top and bottom of the reservoir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modeled processes include two-phase flow of CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and water subject to relative permeability and capillary effects, change of fluid density, viscosity, and CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; solubility with pressure and salinity, and formation dry-out with precipitation of salt. Salt precipitation is monitored and quantified by the change of solid saturation, which is the fraction of pore volume occupied by salt. The resulting porosities are calculated from the solid saturation values and the permeabilities are estimated using the implemented porosity-permeability relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/PruessSchematic.png" alt="K. Pruess and Müller (2009)"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="results-comparison"&gt;Results comparison&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation predicts that permeability decreases to almost zero near the injection well, while the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; relation predicts that the final permeability is around 50% of the initial permeability near the injection well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/kred.png"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systematic experiments are in need to validate the porosity-permeability relations proposed by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt;. Such experiments should include measurement of porosity and permeability in well defined representative element volumes. Two mechanisms could cause severe reduction of core permeability, although this reduction should not be double accounted for by the porosity-permeability relation intended for the REVs as discussed above. One mechanism is the capillary driven back flow that transport brine to close to the injection surface. Pore space is thus filled with more salt at these locations. The other possible mechanism is a boundary effect at the injection surface. Since the brine at the injection surface is fully exposed to CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; gas, and initially the brine occupies all pore space at the injection surface, it is possible that this brine will all evaporate and leave the entire injection surface clogged. The core permeability will be zero with this one surface clogged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field observation of salt precipitation in CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; sequestration projects have not been reported yet, but will be invaluable once available. Such observations can be used to confirm whether salt precipitation is severe at the injection surface, and whether capillary back flow is important at conditions encountered in field operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="literature-cited" class="unnumbered"&gt;Literature Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-andre2014well"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andre, Laurent, Yannick Peysson, and Mohamed Azaroual. 2014. “Well Injectivity During Co 2 Storage Operations in Deep Saline Aquifers–Part 2: Numerical Simulations of Drying, Salt Deposit Mechanisms and Role of Capillary Forces.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 22. Elsevier: 301–12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-bacci2013experimental"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bacci, Giacomo, Sevket Durucan, and Anna Korre. 2013. “Experimental and Numerical Study of the Effects of Halite Scaling on Injectivity and Seal Performance During Co 2 Injection in Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Procedia&lt;/em&gt; 37. Elsevier: 3275–82.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-bacci2011experimental"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bacci, Giacomo, Anna Korre, and Sevket Durucan. 2011. “Experimental Investigation into Salt Precipitation During Co 2 Injection in Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Procedia&lt;/em&gt; 4. Elsevier: 4450–6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-baumann2014monitoring"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baumann, G, J Henninges, and M De Lucia. 2014. “Monitoring of Saturation Changes and Salt Precipitation During Co 2 Injection Using Pulsed Neutron-Gamma Logging at the Ketzin Pilot Site.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 28. Elsevier: 134–46.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-carman1997fluid"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carman, PC. 1997. “Fluid Flow Through Granular Beds.” &lt;em&gt;Chemical Engineering Research and Design&lt;/em&gt; 75. Elsevier: S32–S48.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-carman1956flow"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carman, Philip Crosbie. 1956. &lt;em&gt;Flow of Gases Through Porous Media&lt;/em&gt;. Academic press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-giorgis20072d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giorgis, Thomas, Michele Carpita, and Alfredo Battistelli. 2007. “2D Modeling of Salt Precipitation During the Injection of Dry Co 2 in a Depleted Gas Reservoir.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Conversion and Management&lt;/em&gt; 48 (6). Elsevier: 1816–26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-grude2014pressure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grude, S, M Landrø, and J Dvorkin. 2014. “Pressure Effects Caused by Co 2 Injection in the Tubåen Fm., the Snøhvit Field.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 27. Elsevier: 178–87.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-guyant2015salt"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guyant, Ethan, Weon Shik Han, Kue-Young Kim, Myong-Ho Park, and Byoung-Yeop Kim. 2015. “Salt Precipitation and Co 2/Brine Flow Distribution Under Different Injection Well Completions.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 37. Elsevier: 299–310.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-kleinitz2003halite"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kleinitz, W, G Dietzsch, and M Köhler. 2003. “Halite Scale Formation in Gas-Producing Wells.” &lt;em&gt;Chemical Engineering Research and Design&lt;/em&gt; 81 (3). Elsevier: 352–58.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-liu2013permeability"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liu, Hui-Hai, Guoxiang Zhang, ZhenLian Yi, and Yingxue Wang. 2013. “A Permeability-Change Relationship in the Dryout Zone for Co 2 Injection into Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 15. Elsevier: 42–47.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-miri2015new"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miri, Rohaldin, Reinier van Noort, Per Aagaard, and Helge Hellevang. 2015. “New Insights on the Physics of Salt Precipitation During Injection of Co 2 into Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 43. Elsevier: 10–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-mualem1976new"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mualem, Yechezkel. 1976. “A New Model for Predicting the Hydraulic Conductivity of Unsaturated Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resour. Res&lt;/em&gt; 12 (3): 513–22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-muller2009co2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muller, Nadja, Ran Qi, Elizabeth Mackie, Karsten Pruess, and Martin J Blunt. 2009. “CO2 Injection Impairment Due to Halite Precipitation.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Procedia&lt;/em&gt; 1 (1). Elsevier: 3507–14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-ott2015salt"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ott, H, SM Roels, and K De Kloe. 2015. “Salt Precipitation Due to Supercritical Gas Injection: I. Capillary-Driven Flow in Unimodal Sandstone.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 43. Elsevier: 247–55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-pearce1996natural"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pearce, JM, S Holloway, H Wacker, MK Nelis, C Rochelle, and K Bateman. 1996. “Natural Occurrences as Analogues for the Geological Disposal of Carbon Dioxide.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Conversion and Management&lt;/em&gt; 37 (6). Elsevier: 1123–8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-peysson2014well"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peysson, Yannick, Laurent Andre, and Mohamed Azaroual. 2014. “Well Injectivity During Co 2 Storage Operations in Deep Saline Aquifers—Part 1: Experimental Investigation of Drying Effects, Salt Precipitation and Capillary Forces.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 22. Elsevier: 291–300.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-pruess1991tough2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pruess, Karsten. 1991. &lt;em&gt;TOUGH2: A General-Purpose Numerical Simulator for Multiphase Fluid and Heat Flow&lt;/em&gt;. Lawrence Berkeley Lab. Berkeley, Calif.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-pruess2009formation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pruess, Karsten, and Nadja Müller. 2009. “Formation Dry-Out from Co2 Injection into Saline Aquifers: 1. Effects of Solids Precipitation and Their Mitigation.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resources Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (3). Wiley Online Library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-pruess2007eco2n"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pruess, Karsten, and Nicolas Spycher. 2007. “ECO2N–A Fluid Property Module for the Tough2 Code for Studies of Co 2 Storage in Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;Energy Conversion and Management&lt;/em&gt; 48 (6). Elsevier: 1761–7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-qiao2014compositional"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qiao, C, L Li, RT Johns, and J Xu. 2014. “Compositional Modeling of Reaction-Induced Injectivity Alteration During Co2 Flooding in Carbonate Reservoirs. Paper Spe-170930 Presented at the Spe Annual Technical Conference and Exhibition Amsterdam, the Netherlands, 27-29 October.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-roels2016capillary"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roels, Saskia M, Ntiana El Chatib, Costas Nicolaides, and Pacelli LJ Zitha. 2016. “Capillary-Driven Transport of Dissolved Salt to the Drying Zone During&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;∖&lt;/span&gt; Hbox &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;Co&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; _ &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;2&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; Injection in Homogeneous and Layered Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;Transport in Porous Media&lt;/em&gt;. Springer, 1–14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-tang2015experimental"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tang, Yong, Ruizhi Yang, Zhimin Du, and Fanhua Zeng. 2015. “Experimental Study of Formation Damage Caused by Complete Water Vaporization and Salt Precipitation in Sandstone Reservoirs.” &lt;em&gt;Transport in Porous Media&lt;/em&gt; 107 (1). Springer: 205–18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-verma1988thermohydrological"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verma, A, and K Pruess. 1988. “Thermohydrological Conditions and Silica Redistribution Near High-Level Nuclear Wastes Emplaced in Saturated Geological Formations.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth (1978–2012)&lt;/em&gt; 93 (B2). Wiley Online Library: 1159–73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-wang2010halite"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wang, Y, T Luce, C Ishizawa, M Shuck, K Smith, H Ott, and M Appel. 2010. “Halite Precipitation and Permeability Assessment During Supercritical Co2 Core Flood.” In &lt;em&gt;International Symposium of the Society of Core Analysis, Halifax&lt;/em&gt;, 4–7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-xu2004reactive"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xu, Tianfu, Yvette Ontoy, Phil Molling, Nicolas Spycher, Mauro Parini, and Karsten Pruess. 2004. “Reactive Transport Modeling of Injection Well Scaling and Acidizing at Tiwi Field, Philippines.” &lt;em&gt;Geothermics&lt;/em&gt; 33 (4). Elsevier: 477–91.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-zeidouni2009analytical"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zeidouni, Mehdi, Mehran Pooladi-Darvish, and David Keith. 2009. “Analytical Solution to Evaluate Salt Precipitation During Co 2 Injection in Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 3 (5). Elsevier: 600–611.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>carbon sequestration</category><category>dry out</category><category>reservoir clogging</category><guid>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/posts/zhang2016clogging.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2017 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>