<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Thoughts, opinions, and research projects (Posts about reactive transport)</title><link>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/categories/reactive-transport.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:39:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>How do minerals reactions change multiphase flow properties in reactive transport modeling</title><link>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/posts/zhang2016constitutive.html</link><dc:creator>Shuo Zhang</dc:creator><description>&lt;!--
.. title: How do minerals reactions change multiphase flow properties in reactive transport modeling
.. slug: zhang2016constitutive
.. date: 2017-03-29 
.. tags: Mineral reactions, multiphase flow properties, reactive transport, constitutive relations
.. link: 
.. description: 
.. type: text
--&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to model geochemical reactions together with subsurface flow and solute transport, reactive transport modeling (RTM) is receiving increasing interest &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(C. I. Steefel, DePaolo, and Lichtner 2005)&lt;/span&gt;. RTM refers to the creation of computer models that integrate chemical reactions with the transport of fluids through the Earth’s crust. Such models predict the distribution in space and time of the chemical reactions that occur along a flow path. Today, RTM has become an essential tool for the analysis of coupled physical, chemical, and biological processes in Earth systems. The advantage of this approach is that it links individual time- and space-dependent processes in complex natural systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to model hydro-geochemical problems on a large scale, RTM employs continuum representations of the porous medium and assumes the existence of a representative elementary volume where, for instance, flow can be described by Darcy’s law &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(C. I. Steefel, DePaolo, and Lichtner 2005)&lt;/span&gt;. A porous medium is treated as continuous domains with macroscopic flow and transport parameters such as hydraulic conductivity, porosity, dispersivity, as well as geochemical parameters such as reactive surface area and reaction rates. However, geochemical reactions such as mineral dissolution/precipitation modify the porous medium’s pore structure. An up-scaling procedure is needed to predict changes in hydraulic properties such as permeability, capillary pressure, and relative permeabilities within the framework of continuum-scale flow and transport models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently the effects of chemical reactions on flow properties are represented as a relation between permeability and porosity in reactive transport modeling. Porosity is updated after chemical calculations from the change of mineral volumes, then permeability change is calculated from the porosity change using an empirical permeability-porosity relation, most commonly the Carman-Kozeny relation &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Kozeny 1927; Carman 1956)&lt;/span&gt;, or the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; relation. To the best of our knowledge, there are no closed-form relations available yet for the effects of chemical reactions on multi-phase flow properties, and thus currently these effects cannot be accounted for in reactive transport modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper presents new constitutive relations to represent how chemical reactions affect multi-phase flow properties on the continuum scale based on the conceptual model of parallel capillary tubes. The parameters in our new relations are either pre-existing input in a multi-phase flow simulation (initial capillary pressure function), or intermediate modeling results (water saturation, changes in mineral volume). With those parameters the new relations can be implemented in an existing reactive transport simulator directly, without introducing new variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change of porosity, permeability, and multi-phase flow parameters due to mineral reactions in a porous medium can be caused by different mechanisms in different scenarios. For example, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt; investigate permeability change due to salt precipitation in the context of CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; injection. The rational for this process is that during CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; injection, water evaporates into the CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; stream. Salinity starts to increase in the water and salt eventually precipitates out. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;K. Pruess and Müller (2009)&lt;/span&gt; discuss how this ’dry out’ will impact injectivity by modeling the permeability change due to salt precipitation. Reduction of permeability can also be a consequence of bacterial growth in a porous medium as a consequence of groundwater recharge, water treatment or disposal processes, enhanced oil recovery schemes, or in-situ bioremediation of organic contaminants in groundwater &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Taylor and Jaffé 1990; Ginn et al. 2002; &lt;span class="citeproc-not-found" data-reference-id="schafer1998simulation"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. Plugging can be particularly severe for water injection and bioremediation projects, since both processes inject water containing relatively high levels of growth substrate and inorganic nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mineral dissolution occurs where acid reacts with the surfaces of a porous medium. A common method of stimulating oil wells to achieve greater production is to inject acid into an oil bearing formation with the hope of significantly increasing the permeability in some region around the wellbore. The reacting acid will dissolve a portion of the porous solid thus changing the pore structure. The extent to which this dissolution of solid enhances permeability of the reservoir is essential to the design of an effective acid treatment &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Schechter and Gidley 1969; Hiorth, Cathles, and Madland 2010)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relation between porosity change and permeability change is also relevant to the effects of diagenesis such as cementation or dissolution on reservoir quality prediction. Depending on the chemical and crystallographic properties, cements fill the intergranular pores and increase the tortuosity of the permeable medium. The result is a reduction in permeability compared to unaltered rock. The uncertainty of the location and chemical composition of various cements makes it difficult to predict their effects on permeability &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Panda and Lake 1995; Bjørkum and Nadeau 1998)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is intended to provide the fundamental basis for making reliable estimates of the influence of pore structure on multi-phase flow properties. Our approach should yield results pertinent to the problems cited above. Indeed, any problem concerned with interaction of the porous solid-fluid system and its effects on multi-phase flow properties should be susceptible to arguments similar to these presented here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="previous-relations"&gt;Previous Relations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mineral dissolution and precipitation reactions in subsurface porous media alter the structure of the pore network. The changes in pore structure manifest themselves in the constitutive relations that characterize the continuum-scale properties of the medium and are used in the governing equations of flow and transport. The question is how these effects can be accurately captured in modeling reactive transport in reservoirs. The porosity changes caused by mineral reactions can be easily related to precipitation or dissolution volume, but the permeability change associated with a change in porosity is a more complex problem, as the porosity-permeability correlations depend on many geometric factors such as pore-size distribution, pore shapes, and connectivity. Since there is a wide variation in these geometric properties among natural rock formations, the porosity-permeability correlations will generally depend on the rock type and will be site specific. Attempts to obtain this relationship by many investigators have produced results which differ considerably from each other. For example, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Mavis and Wilsey (1937)&lt;/span&gt; found the permeability of filter sands to be proportional to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, while &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Brace (1977)&lt;/span&gt; found a 3rd power correlation with porosity for crystalline rocks. It is therefore obvious that no simple general correlation between porosity and permeability can be applied to all permeable materials. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Xie et al. (2014)&lt;/span&gt; discusses the implementation of permeability-porosity relationship in several reactive transport codes and conducted benchmark problems, but only the Carman-Kozeny relation is used in their models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact we do not need an absolute permeability-porosity correlation but the relationship between their relative changes. Many investigators have proposed such relationships for different materials in which the porosity changes were brought about by different physical mechanisms. The straight capillary models have been frequently employed. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt; assume that the medium has a set of non-intersecting flow channels with either circular tubular or planar cross sections, and construct series of models that are able to represent pore throat effects. Minor changes in average porosity cause drastic permeability changes due to closure of the pore throats in their model, and they find that there is a non-zero critical porosity &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; at which permeability reduces to zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relations above assume that mineral dissolution and precipitation reactions occur in all pores and ignore the important fact that for multiphase flow, these reactions only occur in pores occupied by the water phase. For example, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ott, Roels, and De Kloe (2015)&lt;/span&gt; observe in their CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; coring flooding experiment that precipitated salt occupies complementary space with initial CO&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; gas, and the overlap between salt precipitation and initial gas overlap less than 5%. As a result, these traditional approaches are applicable to the single-phase flow condition only, while multiphase flow is common in oil and gas reservoirs, geothermal reservoirs, geological carbon storage, and groundwater remediation. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; use the concept of multi-phase flow in calculating the change of permeability due to a change in porosity. These authors argue that in multi-phase flow conditions, precipitation occurs only in the pore space occupied by brine, which corresponds to the small capillary tubes in the capillary tube model, since in most cases water is the wetting phase. They derive the relationship between permeability change and porosity change based on their conceptual model, and verify their predictions of new permeability with experimental results. However, although &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; provide the relation of permeability change and chemical reactions, practical approaches to accurately estimate the effects of mineral dissolution and precipitation reactions on multiphase flow properties are not yet available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pore network models provide opportunities to study the change of hydraulic properties due to reactions because detailed information is available at the pore scale &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Algive et al. 2012)&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Raoof et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; developed a pore-network modeling tool capable of simulating fluid flow and multi-component reactive and adsorptive transport under saturated and variably saturated conditions. Other researchers &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Nogues et al. 2013; Li, Peters, and Celia 2006; Varloteaux, Békri, and Adler 2013)&lt;/span&gt; have also developed similar reactive transport models that are able to simulate the evolution of pore bodies within a network. These models can be used to understand the evolution of porosity and permeability in porous media at the pore scale, and aid in the representation of constitutive relationships such as a porosity-permeability curve that can be used to model larger scale processes in continuum scale models. However, to account for changes in conductivity at the pore-to-pore level due to changes in the pore body volume due to precipitation or dissolution of minerals, assumptions have to be made to correlate the change in volume of the pores to a change in throat diameter. For example, in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Nogues et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt;, it is assumed that all pore throats are cylindrical in shape and have a characteristic diameter, and mineral precipitation or dissolution simply reduces the volume of the system and preferential precipitation/dissolution effects are not taken into account. Thus the conclusions for the porosity-permeability relationship from such models are mostly determined by how the pore-diameter change is related to pore-volume change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="theory-development"&gt;Theory Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach to derive the relation between chemical reactions and changes in capillary pressure and relative permeabilities are described as follows: starting with continuum-scale hydraulic properties, the pore size distribution (PS) function is calculated from the initial capillary pressure curve using the capillary tube concept. Changes in mineral volume through equilibrium or kinetic mineral reactions are then translated to changes in pore radii of the PSD by selectively changing the radii of water occupied pores. The resulting new PSD is converted back to an updated capillary pressure curve, which is then used for computing total permeability and relative permeabilities at the continuum scale. Note that our new development is based on the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Mualem (1976)&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Van Genuchten (1980)&lt;/span&gt; model for capillary pressure and relative permeability (before chemical reactions), but the procedure can be also applied to other models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="change-in-pore-size-distribution"&gt;Change in Pore Size Distribution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pore space of a porous medium is conceptualized as cylindrical capillaries with a continuous distribution of radii &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. A given capillary can be either water-filled or completely dry, depending on the saturation state of the medium. With this geometric idealization, the capillary pressure-water saturation curve can be interpreted to represent continuous cumulative pore-size distributions. In a given portion of the porous medium (in computational terms this would be a cell within the modeled domain), at any time the water content is known. Due to precipitation/dissolution, the pore volumes and pore sizes will change and thus the capillary pressure curve changes also. The maximum radius up to which pores are water-filled and therefore affected by mineral reactions can be calculated from the capillary pressure head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$r = \frac{\zeta}{h}$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt; is the radius of capillary tubes, &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; is the capillary pressure head corresponding to the current effective water saturation &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ζ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the capillary factor &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\zeta = \frac{2\sigma cos \phi}{\rho g}$&lt;/span&gt;. Effective water saturation is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\bar{S}=\frac{S-S_r}{1-S_{r}},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the wetting-phase saturation (the ratio of wetting-phase volume to the corresponding bulk volume of pore space), and subscript &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; refers to the residual water saturation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capillary pressure head &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; can be related to effective wetting-phase saturation by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Van Genuchten (1980)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\bar{S}=[1+(\alpha h)^{n}]^{-m},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;em&gt;m=1-1/n&lt;/em&gt; are empirical parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before mineral reactions occur, the relative permeability of the wetting phase &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; can be expressed by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Mualem (1976)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_r=\bar{S}^{1/2} [\dfrac{\int_0^{\bar{s}} (1/h(x))dx}{\int_0^1 (1/h(x))dx}]^2 .$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the mathematical relation &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Van Genuchten 1980)&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$F(\bar{S})=\dfrac{\int_0^{\bar{s}} (1/h(x))dx}{\int_0^1 (1/h(x))dx}=1-(1-\bar{S}^{1/m})^m,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we have &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_{r}(\bar{S})=\bar{S}^{1/2}[1-(1-\bar{S}^{1/m})^m]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes in pore geometry during mineral precipitation or dissolution are complex. However, in order to obtain a closed-form result, we need to make some simplifications. Here we assume a strict dependency of mineral reactions on solution concentrations. In other words, the amount of dissolved or precipitated mineral in a given pore is linearly dependent on its pore volume. Also, we assume that the change in pore volume is uniform within a given pore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we denote the brine saturation at the time when mineral reaction starts as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, then we can define the ratio of the pore volume after chemical reactions to that before reactions, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\beta=\dfrac{S_p-S_{reaction}}{S_p},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the content of precipitated or dissolved mineral, defined as the volume of mineral change divided by the bulk volume of pore space, and is positive for precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a porosity change from &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of a porous medium due to mineral dissolution or precipitation, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; can be calculated as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\beta = 1-\dfrac{(\phi_0-\phi)/\phi_0}{S_p}.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ratio &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; of the radius (for a pore after precipitation/dissolution) to its original radius can be approximated to be a power function of the corresponding volume ratio &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Liu et al. 2013)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\delta=\dfrac{r^*}{r}=\beta^{\chi},$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the radius after precipitation/dissolution, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the original radius, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;χ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is an empirical parameter equal to 4.5. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; discussed this power law in detail. They selected the value of 4.5 to be consistent with patchy distribution of deposits, which was observed from scanning electron micrograph study where salt crystal did not distribute uniformly within a pore, but grew inwardly. Readers are referred to the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; paper and references therein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous study by &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Verma and Pruess (1988)&lt;/span&gt;, changes in mineral volume were modeled as affecting the entire pore spectrum even though mineral reactions occur only in the water-filled part of the pore space. Here we only translate changes in mineral volumes to pore radii in the wet part of the porous medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a given portion of the porous medium, at any time the water saturation is known. The maximum radius up to which pores are water-filled and therefore affected by mineral reactions is calculated as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$r_{p}=\alpha \zeta [\bar{S}_p^{-1/m}-1]^{-1/n}.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The radius &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; divides the pore spectrum into a dry, inert part and a wet reactive part, which compensates for the change in mineral volume. For the calculation of the new PSD, only the pore radii of the wet pore space are multiplied by the proportionality factor &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="capillary-pressure"&gt;Capillary Pressure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calculation of change in capillary pressure after mineral reactions is straightforward since capillary pressure is proportional to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Since the radius is changed from &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; and remains unchanged for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the new capillary pressure head is &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;)/&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; if &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;)=&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; if &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the initial capillary pressure head at saturation &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. This means that capillary pressure is increased by a factor of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in the case of precipitation (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; 1&lt;/span&gt;), and unchanged for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Note that the new &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; curve is not continuous at &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. This is because that mineral precipitation/dissolution only occurs in the water phase where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="permeability"&gt;Permeability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closed-form equation for permeability change due to mineral reactions is given in &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[(\delta-1)(1-(1-\bar{S}_p^{1/m})^m)+1]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the tortuosity factor, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=1-\bar{S}_p+\delta^2\bar{S}_p$&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; define this tortuosity factor to account for the fact that precipitated minerals impact tortuosity of porous media. This definition allows the tortuosity factor to have desirable values in two important cases: one for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; = 1&lt;/span&gt; (without precipitation) and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$(1-\bar{S}_p)^{1/2}$&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; = 0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we derive this relation using the pore size distribution (PSD) function &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, which will give us a slightly different result. The PSD function can be expressed by differentiation of the cumulative water content with respect to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Ritter and Drake 1945)&lt;/span&gt;. Before chemical reactions,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$f(r)=\dfrac{d\theta(r)}{dr}.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We denote the new PSD function as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;(&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, the new water content as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the new radius as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Recall that we defined the volume ratio before and after reactions as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the radius ratio as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Thus, we have &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;θ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. For &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the new PSD function is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$f^*(r^*)=\dfrac{d\theta^*(r^*)}{dr^*}=\dfrac{\beta}{\delta}f(\dfrac{r^*}{\delta}).$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt;, only the water occupied pores are modified,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^{r_p^*}r^*f^*(r^*)dr^*+\int_{r_p}^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; is the threshold radius below which pores are occupied by water, and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt; = &lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, which is the threshold radius post mineral reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^{r_p} \delta\beta rf(r)dr+\int_{r_p}^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the mathematical relation &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Van Genuchten 1980)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$F(\bar{S})=\dfrac{\int_0^r rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}=1-(1-\bar{S}^{1/m})^m,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we obtain &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{K}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[(\delta\beta-1)(1-(1-\bar{S}_p^{1/m})^m)+1]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="relative-permeability-of-water"&gt;Relative Permeability of Water&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relative permeabilities are defined as the permeability of one phase divided by the saturated permeability, in our case, the saturated permeability of modified porous medium (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). However, for simplicity, we derive our new relative permeabilities as divided by the saturated permeability of the original porous medium (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). These relations can be corrected simply by using the factor &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Let us denote the initial water permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, relative permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the new water permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, relative permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. Following &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Mualem (1976)&lt;/span&gt;, we obtain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_{w0}=\dfrac{K_{w0}}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^r rf(r)dr}{\int_0^{\infty} rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[F(\bar{S})]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=\bar{S}$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the new relative permeability of water is,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_w=\dfrac{K_w}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^r \delta\beta rf(r)dr}{\int_0^{\infty} rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[\delta\beta F(\bar{S})]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=\delta^2 \bar{S}$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the ratio of the new water relative permeability over the initial water relative permeability is, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{k_w}{k_{w0}}=\delta^3\beta^2 .$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_w=\dfrac{K_w}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_0^{r_p} \delta\beta rf(r)dr+\int_{r_p}^r rf(r)dr}{\int_0^{\infty} rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[F(\bar{S})+(\delta\beta-1)F(\bar{S}_p)]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=\delta^2 \bar{S}_p + \bar{S}- \bar{S}_p$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{k_w}{k_{w0}}=(\dfrac{\bar{S}-\bar{S}_p+\delta^2 \bar{S}_p}{\bar{S}})^{1/2}[\dfrac{F(\bar{S})+(\delta\beta-1)F(\bar{S}_p)}{F(\bar{S})}]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="relative-permeability-of-non-wetting-phase"&gt;Relative Permeability of Non-Wetting Phase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;Van Genuchten (1980)&lt;/span&gt; did not give the explicit formulation for the relative permeability of non-wetting phase as a function of effective water saturation, but it is straightforward to derive this given the discussions above. Again, we denote the initial permeability of the non-wetting phase as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, relative permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, and the new permeability of the non-wetting phase as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, relative permeability as &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;g&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. The integration for the relative permeability of non-wetting phase is from &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;∞&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_{g0}=\dfrac{K_{g0}}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_r^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[1-F(\bar{S})]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=1-\bar{S}$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the new relative permeability of non-wetting phase is, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_g=\dfrac{K_g}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_r^{r_p} \delta\beta rf(r)dr + \int_{r_p}^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[1-\delta\beta F(\bar{S})+(\delta\beta -1)F(\bar{S}_p)]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=(\bar{S}_p-\bar{S})\delta^2+(1-\bar{S}_p)$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{k_g}{k_{g0}}=[\dfrac{(\bar{S}_p-\bar{S})\delta^2+(1-\bar{S}_p)}{1-\bar{S}}]^{1/2}[\dfrac{1-\delta\beta F(\bar{S})+(\delta\beta -1)F(\bar{S}_p)}{1-F(\bar{S})}]^2.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$k_{g}=\dfrac{K_{g}}{K_0}=\tau^{1/2}[\dfrac{\int_r^\infty rf(r)dr}{\int_0^\infty rf(r)dr}]^2=\tau^{1/2}[1-F(\bar{S})]^2,$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\tau=1-\bar{S}$&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, &lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="math display"&gt;$$\dfrac{k_g}{k_{g0}}=1.$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="verification-with-pore-network-modeling"&gt;Verification with Pore Network Modeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to test the new equations for calculating changes of capillary pressure and relative permeabilities due to mineral precipitation and dissolution, we use pore network modeling (PNM) to compute these functions in a two-phase flow system. The model comprises a constrained set of parameters that mimic the pore structure of a porous medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PNM is commonly used to predict capillary pressure and relative permeability functions for multi-phase flow simulations, and uses idealized geometric representations of complex pore structures and principles of percolation/invasion theory &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Blunt 2001; Blunt et al. 2013)&lt;/span&gt;. It is a well-established approach for calculating the small-scale petrophysical functions of two- and three-phase flow through porous media. Here we use the pore-network model of &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Ryazanov, Van Dijke, and Sorbie (2009)&lt;/span&gt;. This model can be applied to complex unstructured pore-networks, considers film and layer-flow using thermodynamic criteria, uses a variety of shapes to represent the shapes of the pore throats, and has been extensively validated using experimental data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="initial-pore-network-model"&gt;Initial Pore Network Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use a realistic 3D pore-network extracted from pore-space reconstruction methods and CT images that are geometrically and topologically equivalent to the pore structures of a Berea sandstone sample. The network consists of 12349 pores bodies (nodes) and 26146 pore throats (bonds). Each pore is assigned a regular shape (triangle, star, or circle) based on the shape factor which best matches that of the real pore shape. The average coordination number of this pore network is 4.19, initial permeability is 1639.47 mD, and porosity is 0.24. In this numerical experiment, we start with a fully water-saturated network (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; = 1.0&lt;/span&gt;). Then, the non-wetting phase is injected into the network for primary drainage. The pore network model calculates the capillary pressure curve and relative permeability curves as a function of water saturation through flooding. All floods are assumed to be capillary dominated and are simulated according to invasion-percolation principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/PNM.jpg" alt="Snap shot of the Berea pore network model at water saturation of 0.5." width="500"&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Snap shot of the Berea pore network model at water saturation of 0.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial capillary pressure curve and relative permeability curves are shown for this pore network. They are calculated by running primary drainage of non-wetting phase through an initially water-saturated sample. As can be determined in the following figures, the residual saturation of water is 0.24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/vanPc.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/vanKr.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to determine a reasonable value for the parameter &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, we use the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Van Genuchten (1980)&lt;/span&gt; equation to fit the capillary pressure curve. Resulting parameters from fitting the capillary pressure curve are &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; = 0.748, &lt;em&gt;α&lt;/em&gt; = 0.0001994&lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. To test this &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; value on the relative permeability curves, we used the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Van Genuchten (1980)&lt;/span&gt; equations and compared results with the relative permeabilities calculated from pore network modeling. Results show that the van Genuchten/Mualem model presents a satisfactory fit of initial capillary pressure and relative permeability curves. We then use the value of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; to predict how the capillary pressure curve and relative permeabilities change after chemical reactions, for a given amount of dissolved/precipitated minerals. The new capillary pressure and relative permeabilities are calculated from the initial values and the modification factors from our relations. The fitted initial van Genuchten/Mualem curves are not used in these calculation, thus do not affect the results. The main objective in the fitting process is to obtain the value of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; which contains information on the shape of pore size distribution function, and is used in the relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="porosity-permeability-relationship"&gt;Porosity-Permeability Relationship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of comparing pore network modeling results with the new closed-form equations, we select two water saturations of 0.5 and 1.0 as the saturations at which mineral dissolution/precipitation occurs. Here we refer the two cases as the ‘new approach’ and the ‘traditional approach’ respectively since traditionally the relation between flow properties and chemical reactions are built on the assumption of full water saturation. In the new approach, we use the pore network model and run a primary drainage from the initial water-saturated condition to the target water saturation of 0.5. The bonds and nodes that are filled with water were identified in the pore network model when water saturation reaches &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt;. The red is the invaded non-wetting phase at &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt;, while the blue is water. Subsequently, the radii of the water-occupied bonds and nodes were modified by a factor of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for a given porosity change. In the traditional approach, the pore radii of all pores and throats are modified in the pore network model given the same amount of porosity change. This corresponds to the traditional assumption in which chemical reactions are considered to occur in all pores. The modified pore network models using both approaches were flooded again with non-wetting phase starting from a fully water saturated condition to calculate the new permeability, capillary pressure and relative permeability curves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows permeabilities of modified pore network models as a function of porosity change using the two approaches. The values of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; are calculated from the porosity change where &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5, &lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.24&lt;/span&gt;. Given that &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt; ≥ 0&lt;/span&gt;, we have &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;/&lt;em&gt;ϕ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 − &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt;, which means that porosity cannot drop below 50% of its original value given &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt;, because precipitation cannot be more than available pore volume. Ideally porosity does not have an upper limit due to dissolution. However, since the current work only considers the change in pore size, it will not be valid when the porosity increase is large and pore structure is heavily modified. In fact, there will probably be wormholes forming when porosity increases substantially, which has not yet been well modeled. For the range of porosity depicted (0.19-0.27), the value of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ranges from 0.583 to 1.25, and the value of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ranges from 0.088 to 2.73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be observed that using the traditional approach in which precipitation is assumed to happen in all pores and throats, permeability decreases up to 3 orders of magnitude when porosity decreases from 0.24 to 0.19. However, if precipitation is limited in the water occupied pores and throats, only the radii of the small pores and throats are decreased, while the other pores and throats remain unchanged. Thus permeability converges to a value which corresponds to all the unchanged pores and throats and does not decrease to zero. This is well captured by the present model, which we refer to as the modified &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Liu et al. 2013)&lt;/span&gt; model because the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Liu et al. 2013)&lt;/span&gt; model only considered the change in radius but not in volume of the pores after mineral reactions as discussed earlier. The permeability change can be characterized into two regions, a transitional stage from porosity 0.24 to 0.22, and a plateau where permeability is relatively constant when porosity is smaller than 0.22. Most of the permeability is contributed from the unchanged pores and throats on this plateau. The traditional method which assumes that all pores and throats are filled by precipitations fails to capture this result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/PermPoro.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="capillary-pressure-and-relative-permeabilities"&gt;Capillary Pressure and Relative Permeabilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The predicted capillary pressure and relative permeabilities from pore network calculations are compared with our model. Two sets of calculations were conducted and compared. The first set of calculations assumes a decrease of porosity from 0.24 to 0.2015 (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt; = 0.6795, &lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; = 0.1757&lt;/span&gt;), which represents precipitation, and the second set of calculations increases porosity from 0.24 to 0.2592 (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt; = 1.160, &lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt; = 1.952&lt;/span&gt;), which represents dissolution. The dashed lines in all figures are the initial capillary pressure or relative permeabilities. The solid lines represent predictions from our current model and the dots are results from pore network modeling. The initial PNM data is used directly in our model and modifications of this data are applied after dissolution or precipitation based on our new relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capillary pressure is increased by a factor of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;1/&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for water saturation smaller than 0.5,using the new approach, while remains unchanged for water saturation larger than 0.5. Thus, there is an offset at &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt; that is well captured by our model and the pore network calculation. The relative permeability of water is decreased by a factor of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 0.5&lt;/span&gt;. Again, there is an offset at &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; = 0.5&lt;/span&gt;, and the change of relative permeability is less substantial for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; 0.5&lt;/span&gt;. The relative permeability of non-wetting phase is unchanged for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; 0.5&lt;/span&gt;, but reduced for &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;w&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;lt; 0.5&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/PcPcp.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/KrwPcp.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://shuozhangthu.github.io/files/KrgPcp.png" width="500"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the comparisons indicate that our proposed continuum-scale relations satisfactorily predict the pore-scale modeling results. The new method enables calculations of new permeability, capillary pressure and relative permeabilities in reservoir simulators after mineral reactions. It includes parameters that describe pore size distribution (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), the fraction of pore space that is water filled when precipitation happens (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), and the amount of precipitation/dissolution (&lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;δ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;β&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;). The related parameters are either model input (e.g., &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), or intermediate modeling results (e.g., &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;), for calculating two-phase flow, so no new parameters need to be defined in reservoir simulators or reactive transport codes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="discussions-and-conclusions"&gt;Discussions and Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capillary tube model, which is the foundation of the presented model, has several underlying assumptions &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Larson, Scriven, and Davis 1981)&lt;/span&gt;. One is that the connectivity of real porous media and the irregular geometry of real porous matrices and associated effects are ignored. Also this model neglects the water wetting films in pores filled by a non-wetting phase. Hence we cannot model how chemical components diffuse through these water films and eventually react with a (small) fraction of the pore space. Despite these shortcomings, the capillary tube model is widely applied as a simple link between continuum-scale hydraulic properties and PSD’s &lt;span class="citation"&gt;(Taylor and Jaffé 1990)&lt;/span&gt;. In this paper we integrate the concept of modifying pore volumes through mineral reactions into more sophisticated pore network models to relate PSD’s to capillary pressure curve and relative permeabilites. Comparisons between our capillary tube model and pore network model show that satisfactory predictions can be achieved using the capillary tube model for changes in capillary pressure, permeability and relative permeabilites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main contribution in this paper is the advancement of continuum-scale models for the effect of chemical reactions on multi-phase flow properties. One key step in reactive transport modeling is to capture these effects for feedbacks of chemical reaction on fluid flow. Currently in most reactive transport simulators this is limited to estimating permeability change from porosity change. However, due to the fact that permeability is not a single function of porosity, but also a function of pore geometry, the current approach has large uncertainties. In this paper, we adopt the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model for permeability change which not only considers porosity change but also takes into account pore size distribution and water saturation. We extend the &lt;span class="citation"&gt;Liu et al. (2013)&lt;/span&gt; model to multi-phase flow properties, and provide closed-form equations on how capillary pressure and relative permeabilities should change due to chemical reactions. These relations are continuum-scale equations, and can be implemented in reactive transport models directly without introducing additional parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="literature-cited" class="unnumbered"&gt;Literature Cited&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-algive2012impact"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algive, Lionnel, Samir Békri, Fadi H Nader, Olivier Lerat, and Olga Vizika. 2012. “Impact of Diagenetic Alterations on the Petrophysical and Multiphase Flow Properties of Carbonate Rocks Using a Reactive Pore Network Modeling Approach.” &lt;em&gt;Oil &amp;amp; Gas Science and Technology–Revue d’IFP Energies Nouvelles&lt;/em&gt; 67 (1). Technip: 147–60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-bjorkum1998temperature"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bjørkum, Per Arne, and Paul H Nadeau. 1998. “Temperature Controlled Porosity/Permeability Reduction, Fluid Migration, and Petroleum Exploration in Sedimentary Basins.” &lt;em&gt;APPEA Journal&lt;/em&gt; 38 (Part 1): 452–64.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-blunt2001flow"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blunt, Martin J. 2001. “Flow in Porous Media—pore-Network Models and Multiphase Flow.” &lt;em&gt;Current Opinion in Colloid &amp;amp; Interface Science&lt;/em&gt; 6 (3). Elsevier: 197–207.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-blunt2013pore"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blunt, Martin J, Branko Bijeljic, Hu Dong, Oussama Gharbi, Stefan Iglauer, Peyman Mostaghimi, Adriana Paluszny, and Christopher Pentland. 2013. “Pore-Scale Imaging and Modelling.” &lt;em&gt;Advances in Water Resources&lt;/em&gt; 51. Elsevier: 197–216.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-brace1977permeability"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brace, WF. 1977. “Permeability from Resistivity and Pore Shape.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research&lt;/em&gt; 82 (23). Wiley Online Library: 3343–9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-carman1956flow"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carman, Philip Crosbie. 1956. &lt;em&gt;Flow of Gases Through Porous Media&lt;/em&gt;. Academic press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-ginn2002processes"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ginn, Timothy R, Brian D Wood, Kirk E Nelson, Timothy D Scheibe, Ellyn M Murphy, and T Prabhakar Clement. 2002. “Processes in Microbial Transport in the Natural Subsurface.” &lt;em&gt;Advances in Water Resources&lt;/em&gt; 25 (8). Elsevier: 1017–42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-hiorth2010impact"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiorth, A, LM Cathles, and MV Madland. 2010. “The Impact of Pore Water Chemistry on Carbonate Surface Charge and Oil Wettability.” &lt;em&gt;Transport in Porous Media&lt;/em&gt; 85 (1). Springer: 1–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-kozeny1927uber"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kozeny, Josef. 1927. &lt;em&gt;Über Kapillare Leitung Des Wassers Im Boden:(Aufstieg, Versickerung Und Anwendung Auf Die Bewässerung)&lt;/em&gt;. Hölder-Pichler-Tempsky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-larson1981percolation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larson, RG, LE Scriven, and HT Davis. 1981. “Percolation Theory of Two Phase Flow in Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;Chemical Engineering Science&lt;/em&gt; 36 (1). Elsevier: 57–73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-li2006upscaling"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Li, Li, Catherine A Peters, and Michael A Celia. 2006. “Upscaling Geochemical Reaction Rates Using Pore-Scale Network Modeling.” &lt;em&gt;Advances in Water Resources&lt;/em&gt; 29 (9). Elsevier: 1351–70.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-liu2013permeability"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liu, Hui-Hai, Guoxiang Zhang, ZhenLian Yi, and Yingxue Wang. 2013. “A Permeability-Change Relationship in the Dryout Zone for Co 2 Injection into Saline Aquifers.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 15. Elsevier: 42–47.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-mavis1937filter"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mavis, FT, and EF Wilsey. 1937. “Filter Sand Permeability Studies.” &lt;em&gt;Eng. News Rec&lt;/em&gt; 118: 299–300.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-mualem1976new"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mualem, Yechezkel. 1976. “A New Model for Predicting the Hydraulic Conductivity of Unsaturated Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resour. Res&lt;/em&gt; 12 (3): 513–22.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-nogues2013permeability"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nogues, Juan P, Jeffrey P Fitts, Michael A Celia, and Catherine A Peters. 2013. “Permeability Evolution Due to Dissolution and Precipitation of Carbonates Using Reactive Transport Modeling in Pore Networks.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resources Research&lt;/em&gt; 49 (9). Wiley Online Library: 6006–21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-ott2015salt"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ott, H, SM Roels, and K De Kloe. 2015. “Salt Precipitation Due to Supercritical Gas Injection: I. Capillary-Driven Flow in Unimodal Sandstone.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Greenhouse Gas Control&lt;/em&gt; 43. Elsevier: 247–55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-panda1995physical"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panda, Manmath N, and Larry W Lake. 1995. “A Physical Model of Cementation and Its Effects on Single-Phase Permeability.” &lt;em&gt;AAPG Bulletin&lt;/em&gt; 79 (3). American Association of Petroleum Geologists: 431–43.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-pruess2009formation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pruess, Karsten, and Nadja Müller. 2009. “Formation Dry-Out from Co2 Injection into Saline Aquifers: 1. Effects of Solids Precipitation and Their Mitigation.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resources Research&lt;/em&gt; 45 (3). Wiley Online Library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-raoof2013poreflow"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raoof, A, HM Nick, SM Hassanizadeh, and CJ Spiers. 2013. “PoreFlow: A Complex Pore-Network Model for Simulation of Reactive Transport in Variably Saturated Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;Computers &amp;amp; Geosciences&lt;/em&gt; 61. Elsevier: 160–74.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-ritter1945pressure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritter, HL, and LC Drake. 1945. “Pressure Porosimeter and Determination of Complete Macropore-Size Distributions. Pressure Porosimeter and Determination of Complete Macropore-Size Distributions.” &lt;em&gt;Industrial &amp;amp; Engineering Chemistry Analytical Edition&lt;/em&gt; 17 (12). ACS Publications: 782–86.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-ryazanov2009two"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryazanov, AV, MIJ Van Dijke, and KS Sorbie. 2009. “Two-Phase Pore-Network Modelling: Existence of Oil Layers During Water Invasion.” &lt;em&gt;Transport in Porous Media&lt;/em&gt; 80 (1). Springer: 79–99.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-schechter1969change"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schechter, RS, and JL Gidley. 1969. “The Change in Pore Size Distribution from Surface Reactions in Porous Media.” &lt;em&gt;AIChE Journal&lt;/em&gt; 15 (3). Wiley Online Library: 339–50.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-steefel2005reactive"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steefel, Carl I, Donald J DePaolo, and Peter C Lichtner. 2005. “Reactive Transport Modeling: An Essential Tool and a New Research Approach for the Earth Sciences.” &lt;em&gt;Earth and Planetary Science Letters&lt;/em&gt; 240 (3). Elsevier: 539–58.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-taylor1990biofilm"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor, Stewart W, and Peter R Jaffé. 1990. “Biofilm Growth and the Related Changes in the Physical Properties of a Porous Medium: 1. Experimental Investigation.” &lt;em&gt;Water Resources Research&lt;/em&gt; 26 (9). Wiley Online Library: 2153–9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-vangenuchten1980closed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Genuchten, M Th. 1980. “A Closed-Form Equation for Predicting the Hydraulic Conductivity of Unsaturated Soils.” &lt;em&gt;Soil Science Society of America Journal&lt;/em&gt; 44 (5). Soil Science Society of America: 892–98.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-varloteaux2013pore"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Varloteaux, Clément, Samir Békri, and Pierre M Adler. 2013. “Pore Network Modelling to Determine the Transport Properties in Presence of a Reactive Fluid: From Pore to Reservoir Scale.” &lt;em&gt;Advances in Water Resources&lt;/em&gt; 53. Elsevier: 87–100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-verma1988thermohydrological"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verma, A, and K Pruess. 1988. “Thermohydrological Conditions and Silica Redistribution Near High-Level Nuclear Wastes Emplaced in Saturated Geological Formations.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth (1978–2012)&lt;/em&gt; 93 (B2). Wiley Online Library: 1159–73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-xie2014implementation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xie, Mingliang, K Ulrich Mayer, Francis Claret, Peter Alt-Epping, Diederik Jacques, Carl Steefel, Christophe Chiaberge, and Jiri Simunek. 2014. “Implementation and Evaluation of Permeability-Porosity and Tortuosity-Porosity Relationships Linked to Mineral Dissolution-Precipitation.” &lt;em&gt;Computational Geosciences&lt;/em&gt;. Springer, 1–17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>constitutive relations</category><category>Mineral reactions</category><category>multiphase flow properties</category><category>reactive transport</category><guid>http://shuozhangthu.github.io/posts/zhang2016constitutive.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>